Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we're tackling a
very difficult issue for
many English learners.
We're talking about taking things
from other people and giving them back.
That's right, so today we are going to talk
about money and we're going to lend money
and borrow money and
we're going to talk more
about this after we
listen to the dialogue.
Can I borrow five bucks?
No, come on, I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
Last time I went to many,
you never paid me back.
I promise if you lend me five dollars
today, I will repay you in four next week.
Okay, but I'm taking your
skateboard as collateral.
Fine, I can't believe you don't trust me.
It's nothing personal, just business.
All right, so now let's take a look at
that language on language takeaway.
So first up, we have the key verbs for
today, the verb to borrow and to lend.
Now this is a really important
difference to make because
many people make this mistake
where they use the wrong verb.
Now, if I ask you Marco,
can I borrow your bicycle?
That means can I take
your bicycle from you and
then later I'll give it
back, but I want to use it.
Right, so the verb
is kind of reflexive.
It's going on to you.
You want to borrow, right?
I want to borrow. I want to
take it from you for a short
time and then I want to
give it back. So to borrow.
Right. Now the other verb is to lend and
then on the other hand goes from me to you.
So you borrow my bicycle.
I lend you my bicycle. I give it to you.
That's right. So another way of asking,
can I borrow is can you lend me your bike?
That means can you act?
Can you do this thing for me?
So there's two of different
ways of saying it and it's
very important to remember
who is doing what exactly.
So remember the person taking is
borrowing, the person giving is lending.
So it's not correct and
remember to and it's not
correct to say, can you
borrow me your bicycle?
That's not right. No,
can you lend me?
Like, can you lend me a
hand? Can you help me?
Right. So remember this, to borrow is
something I do. I want to borrow from you.
It's the person, the subject
and the sentence, but
in the case of lending,
someone else is doing it.
So can you lend to me
or can you lend it to him?
You have to say
who it's being lent to?
Exactly. And as you said, who is being
lent to? So the past tense of lend is lent.
Yeah. So Marco lent me his
bike last week and I broke it.
So now I have to pay
him a lot of money.
You have to pay me five bucks
and that's their next word, bucks.
Bucks. Now this is a slang term. So this is
something we say, very casually in America.
When we want to talk
about dollars, right?
So one buck is one dollar. A
hundred bucks is a hundred dollars.
All right. Now, as you
said, it's very American.
You wouldn't really
use it like, I don't know,
if you're in Britain, you wouldn't say a
hundred bucks. No, you would say quid quid.
Exactly. So they don't have dollars.
So they don't say bucks not in England.
All right. Very good. So we
wanted to borrow five dollars.
And well, he's and that person
promised to pay you back on Tuesday.
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
All right. So this is a lot like that
verb to lend to lend him to pay you.
You have to say who
you're going to pay, right?
So Marco, I'm sorry
about your bicycle.
I will pay you back
tomorrow. Okay.
That means I will give
you money for it tomorrow.
So if you borrow money,
you have to pay it back.
All right. So I want
to borrow five dollars.
I promise I will pay
you back Thursday.
Very good. Okay. And now
lastly, we will lend money.
But of course, we need a
guarantee. We make, we need
something to make sure
that you will pay me back.
So that's called
collateral. All right.
Now collateral is important
because sometimes you can't,
you can't trust someone
like you say Marco.
And so, for example, if
I want to rent a bicycle,
so I want to use it for
the day, maybe there's
a store that they
rent bicycles, people.
I would give my passport or
my driver's license as collateral
because I will definitely
return to take my
that driver's license
or passport back.
So that's that's basically a
sign of promise, money or
identification or some
object. That's right.
So usually, for example, if
you're going to get a very
big loan at the bank,
they will ask you for
something as collateral.
So maybe you will have to
give them your
house as collateral.
So you're saying if I can't pay you
back, then you can take my house.
That's right. So
collateral is the last word
in language takeaway.
But we do have some great
phrases for you coming
up in fluency builder.
Can I borrow five
bucks? No, come on.
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
Last time I went to money, you
never paid me back. I
promise if you led me five
dollars today, I will repay
you in full next week.
Okay. But I'm taking your
skateboard as collateral.
Fine. I can't believe you don't trust me.
It's nothing personal. Just business.
All right. We're back. So let's take a
look at these phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder. So
Mark, are these are two
friends talking and the
way they talk to each
other is very casual,
right? So we hear at the
beginning, can I borrow
five bucks? No, come on.
Right. So what
does this come on?
It's, it's a persuasive phrase.
It's one of those phrases where
you're trying to convince
or persuade people and you
can use it as an interjection
in many situations.
So for example, here, come on, lend it to
me, lend me some money. I'll pay you back.
You're trying to convince
that. Please. Yes. Exactly.
But what about this
situation? I'm running late.
I have to go. And my
friend, she's still sitting
at her desk, maybe at
work and just taking forever.
I say, come on. Let's go.
Right. It's like hurry up, move it.
All right. So it's
a way of getting
someone to do something.
You want them to follow you.
Exactly. And now talking
about money again,
the person promised
to repay the money.
He said, I'll pay you back
on Tuesday. But then he also
said, I will repay you
in full next week in full.
Now remember, this is
important. I will repay you in full.
That means I won't repay you a
little bit. And then a little bit later,
I will repay you everything
next week. Right. Exactly.
So if you have to pay
or repay someone in full,
you have to give
them the entire amount.
Not just a part of
it. That's right. In full.
Full means everything. And
the final phrase is the very last
line of today's dialogue.
It's nothing personal.
It's just business. I think
this is a common phrase
when the people use
when maybe doing business
with friends or people,
you know, you know, maybe
you're asking for collateral and the guys
like, I can't believe you don't trust me.
And I'm your brother. And
he's like, it's nothing personal.
It's just business. It's
a way to say, listen,
this is not about you and
me. This is about my rules.
And when I give
something to someone, I
always ask for collateral.
So it's just business.
It's just my way of
doing this. Exactly.
So it's a good phrase to use if you're
doing maybe business with a friend.
And of course, maybe you're setting these
rules and the friend, maybe your friend
feels a little bit offended. You say, hey,
it's nothing personal. It's just business.
Nothing personal. So
that's the last phrase.
Let's take a listen to
the dialogue again.
And we'll be right back.
Can I borrow five bucks? No. Come on.
I'll pay you back on Tuesday.
Last time I went to many, you never paid
me back. I promise if you led me $5 today,
I will repay you in
full next week. Okay.
But I'm taking your
skateboard as collateral.
Fine. I can't believe you don't trust me.
It's nothing personal. Just business.
All right. So lending
money, borrowing money.
Now, as you, as we
mentioned, sometimes you have
people that ask you for
money. Now, did you ever
have that friend that
always asks you for money
and never repaid you? Yes. Like a dollar
at a time like a $8 can borrow a dollar.
It kind of borrow $5. Yeah,
always. And actually this
friend, he would borrow
$10. And he would say, oh,
I'll buy you a coffee tomorrow. I say,
what, a $10 coffee? I don't think so.
So it was always uneven.
I paid more and he never repaid me in full.
It's full, right. So
yeah. And actually, I
think if you add up all
those little amount of
money that maybe some friends borrowed
from you would be a quite a decent amount.
I had many friends who would
be like, hey, can I borrow a
dollar or, you know, even
like 25 cents at a time?
It would add up over
a couple of years. Yeah.
That's, that's like a
whole dinner. Exactly. So,
what do you call these
people? The, the word
in English, that's a slang
word is called a mooch.
A mooch, right. He's
a mooch. It means he's
always taking money
from people or asking other
people to pay for his dinner
or staying at someone's house.
So a mooch is someone
who tries to get things
for free. Right.
That's exactly it.
I had friends like this
that would for food as well,
like maybe I brought my
lunch. This is in school, obviously.
And they would mooch off me,
like, half my sandwich or half my juice.
Can I have some chips? Can I
have some juice? Yeah, exactly.
That's, yeah, that's
mooch behavior.
So that's the verb to mooch
off someone. Yeah, to mooch off
someone, but it's also
a noun. He's a mooch.
He's a mooch. Very interesting
stuff. Maybe you have a
friend that was a mooch or
maybe even yourself back in the day.
So let us know how it
works in your country.
If you lend money
to people, family
members, do you ask for
collateral? Or do you just
forget about it? Let us know
our website is EnglishPod.
com. We'll see
you guys there. Bye.